A Guide to the Taconic Foundation records FA407
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Grants, 1958-2010; 1; 76.73 Cubic Feet 172 document boxes (including 1 half-box), 2 oversized flat boxes; 2.02 Gigabytes 35 digital files
  - Suffolk Housing Services
    For earlier materials see Presbytery of Long Island: Smith Haven Ministries.
    - 1978-1979 (Box 145, Folder 1436)
    - 1980-1982, 1988 (Box 145, Folder 1437)
  - Summerbridge, 1996-1997 (Box 145, Folder 1438)
    Enrichment program based at Riverdale Country School.
  - Support for Training and Educational Program Services (STEPS), 1993 (Box 145, Folder 1439)
  - Task Force on City-Owned Property
    For later funding, see also files for Parodneck Foundation: Task Force on City-Owned Property.
    - 1978-1979 (Box 145, Folder 1440)
    - 1980-1981 August 5 (Box 145, Folder 1441)
    - 1981 August 5 - October (Box 145, Folder 1442)
  - Taylor, William L., 1969-1970 (Box 146, Folder 1443)
    See also Catholic University of America: Center for National Policy Review.
    Project file. Support for feasibility study on the establishment of a center for research on race and urban issues. Taylor was former director of the U. S. Civil Rights Commission.
  - The Teachers Incorporated
    - 1968-1969 March (Box 146, Folder 1444)
    - 1969 April - December (Box 146, Folder 1445)
    - 1969 April - December (Box 146, Folder 1445 A)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 146, Folder 1446)
    - 1972-1974 (Box 146, Folder 1447)
    - (Literature), circa 1970-1975 (Box 146, Folder 1448)
  - Theatre Incorporated, 1967-1969 (Box 146, Folder 1449)
  - Third Street Music School Settlement, 1979-1981, 1984-1985 (Box 146, Folder 1450)
  - Teachers College. See Columbia University, Teachers College.
  - Totenberg, Amy, 1976 (Box 146, Folder 1451)
    Support for research and legal work concerning the administration of the Community Development Block Grant Program. For the discretionary grant she received, see also Voluntary Defenders Committee, Inc.
  - Tristam, Ed, 1981 (Box 146, Folder 1452)
    File contains brief memo on Weatherization Industry Support Exchange.
  - Trubek, David
    Project file. Trubek was hired as a consultant to help evaluate the "open suburbs movement." The file includes his report, "Urban Systems and Distributive Justice: Rethinking the Open Suburbs Movement."
    See also Center for Public Representation: Trubek, David.
    - 1973 (Box 146, Folder 1453)
    - 1974, 1976 (Box 147, Folder 1454)
  - Trust for Public Land, 1995 (Box 147, Folder 1455)
  - Tuskegee Institute, 1960 (Box 147, Folder 1456)
    File contains Report to the Taconic Foundation on "The Social Readiness of Negro Youth," by Lewis W. Jones and Paul N. Geisel.
  - Twentieth Century Fund: General, 1960-1988 (Box 147, Folder 1457)
    File includes 1966 proposal for foundation support of the commercial theatre.
  - Twentieth Century Fund: National Media Council, 1972-1973 (Box 147, Folder 1458)
  - Twenty-First Century Foundation
    - 1971-1974 (Box 147, Folder 1459)
    - 1975-1977, 1983 (Box 147, Folder 1460)
    - (LIterature), 1972-1977 (Box 147, Folder 1461)
  - Union Settlement Association
    - 1959-1970 (Box 147, Folder 1462)
    - 1971-1973 (Box 148, Folder 1463)
    - 1974-1983 (Box 148, Folder 1464)
    - (Literature), 1975 (Box 148, Folder 1465)
      File contains Evaluation of the College Readiness Program of Union Settlement, January 1975.
  - United Negro College Fund, 1969-1978 (Box 148, Folder 1466)
  - United Neighborhood Houses: General, 2005-2006 (Box 148, Folder 1467)
  - United Neighborhood Houses: Education for Peace, 1976 (Box 148, Folder 1468)
  - United Neighborhood Houses: Interface
    Support for program to coordinate and strengthen management skills at settlement houses.
    - 1974-1976 June (Box 148, Folder 1469)
    - 1976 July - 1977 (Box 148, Folder 1470)
    - 1978, 1981, 1984, 1986-1988 (Box 148, Folder 1471)
  - United Neighborhood Houses: Joint Fund, 1959-1967 (Box 148, Folder 1472)
  - United Neighborhood Houses: Joint Fund, 1968-1971 (Box 148, Folder 1473)
  - United Neighborhood Houses: Stuyvesant Community Center, 1961-1963 (Box 148, Folder 1474)
  - United States, Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1968, 1977-1980 (Box 149, Folder 1475)
  - United States Committee for UNICEF, 1968 (Box 149, Folder 1476)
    In support of the work of the Committee for NIgeria/Biafra Relief.
  - United States Conference of Mayors, 1967, 1980 (Box 149, Folder 1477)
  - United States National Student Association, 1960, 1965 (Box 149, Folder 1478)
    Support for seminar on Southern Civil Rights.
  - University Neighborhood Housing Program
    - 1991-1993 (Box 149, Folder 1479)
    - 1994-1998 (Box 149, Folder 1480)
    - 1999-2002 May (Box 149, Folder 1481)
    - 2002 June-December (Box 149, Folder 1482)
    - 2003 (Box 149, Folder 1483)
    - 2004 (Box 149, Folder 1484)
    - 2005 (Box 149, Folder 1485)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 150, Folder 1486)
  - University of Georgia Press, 1996-1997 (Box 150, Folder 1487)
    Support for distribution of The Potomac Chronicle.
  - University of Minnesota
    Support for Roy Wilkins Chair and Center in Human Relations and Social Justice.
    - 1987-1990 (Box 150, Folder 1488)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 150, Folder 1489)
  - University of North Carolina, 1961-1967 (Box 150, Folder 1490)
    Support for special training program in political science.
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1992-1994 (Box 150, Folder 1491)
    Support for support for Law professor Michael Schill's comparative study of nonprofit housing development in the United States and the United Kingdom.
  - University of Vermont: UVM - Taconic Land Use Study
    - 1972, 1974 January-May (Box 150, Folder 1492)
    - 1974 June-December (Box 150, Folder 1493)
    - 1975-1976, 1994 (Box 150, Folder 1494)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 150, Folder 1494 A)
  - University of Vermont: UVM - Taconic Land Use Study (Press Clippings), 1971-1972 (Box 150, Folder 1495)
  - University of Vermont: UVM - Taconic Land Use Study (Press Clippings), 1973 (Box 150, Folder 1496)
  - University of Vermont: UVM - Taconic Land Use Study (Reports and Literature), 1973-1974 (Box 150, Folder 1497)
  - University of Vermont: UVM - Taconic Land Use Study (Reports and Literature), 1974 (Box 151, Folder 1498)
  - University Settlement Society of New York
    - 1990-1992 (Box 151, Folder 1499)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 151, Folder 1500)
    - 1994 (Box 151, Folder 1501)
  - Urban America
    - Grants
      Taconic Foundation grants for Urban America's general program and for its special program for architects and others in the design profession (in particular, for Architectural Forum).
      - 1964-1966 (Box 151, Folder 1502)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 151, Folder 1503)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 151, Folder 1504)
    - Ad Hoc Committee of Mayors, Urban Coalition Emergency Coalition, 1966-1967 (Box 151, Folder 1505)
    - Architectural Forum
      Under Steven Currier's initiative, Urban America published Architectural Forum from April 1965 through 1969. The journal had previously been published by Time Inc., but publication had lapsed from October 1964 through March 1965. Urban America sold the journal to Whitney Publications as of December 1, 1969.
      - General, 1964-1970 (Box 151, Folder 1506)
        - Architectural Forum, 1965 April - 1970; 2014:FA407:060; 11 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:060)
          A duplicate bound volume containing a set of the July-December 1966 issues was discarded in processing.
          Eleven bound volumes: 1965 April-December 1966 January-June 1966 July-December 1967 January-June 1967 July-December 1968 January-June 1968 July-December 1969 January-June 1969 July-December 1970 January-June 1970 July-December
        - Architectural Forum (Le Corbusier tribute issue), 1965 October; 2014:FA407:061; 2 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:061)
          Two copies of Architectural Forum, volume 123, number 3, October 1965: Le Corbusier - A Tribute. Issue housed in clamshell case.
      - Literature, 1966-1968 (Box 152, Folder 1507)
        Includes history of the Architectural Forum under the sponsorship of Stephen Currier and the Taconic Foundation, April 1965-April 1967, and survey of the readership by architects of five architectural publications.
      - Literature, 1964-1969 (Box 152, Folder 1508)
        Includes advertising samples and analysis of Architectural Forum coverage of subject categories, 1967-1969.
      - Wilkin Report, 1968 December (Box 152, Folder 1509)
        "Renascence of a Dynamic Magazine: A Study of the Resurgent Architectural Forum, Its Field, Market and Competitors - With a Prediction about the Future of the Magazine," by D. B. Wilkin.
      - Wilkin Report, 1968-1969 (Box 152, Folder 1510)
        Report by David Bradford Wilkin on "The Architectural Forum in 1968: Condition and Prospects." File contains correspondence and first draft of the report.
    - Board Meetings
      - 1964-1965 (Box 152, Folder 1511)
        - James E. Lash (portrait), circa 1965 December; 2014:FA407:047; 1 still image (Item 2014:FA407:047)
          Includes press release announcement, circa 1965 December 19, of Lash's appointment as Executive Vice President of Urban America.
      - 1966 (Box 152, Folder 1512)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 152, Folder 1513)
    - Conference "Our People and Their Cities"
      Conference held September 11-13, 1966, in Washington, DC, under the sponsorship of Urban America. The conference was intended as a citizen response to the May 1965 White House Conference on Natural Beauty.
      - General, 1966 (Box 152, Folder 1514)
        - Lady Bird Johnson speaking at "Our People and Their Cities" conference, 1966 September 12; 2014:FA407:048; 1 still image (Item 2014:FA407:048)
      - General, 1965-1967, 1970 (Box 153, Folder 1515)
        File includes correspondence concerning the September 1966 conference and the program of Urban America in general.
      - Background Book, 1966 (Box 153, Folder 1516)
        "Our People and Their Cities: A Background to Urban America's Conference to Improve the Quality of Urban America." Position papers by Frederick Gutheim, commissioned to provide background for roundtable and conference discussions.
      - Conference Packet, 1966 (Box 153, Folder 1517)
        The oversized conference packets are filed separately from this folder, which consists of a placemarker, containing only the separation information.
        Oversize materials have been separated from the file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
        Two sets of conference materials (Program, Chart Book, Roster, and Background Book) in presentation boxes personally labeled for Stephen R. Currier and for Jane Lee Eddy. Currier's box also includes a Ticket Book. Copies of Currier's speech and Jane Lee Eddy's comments are also loosely inserted in his copy of the box.
        - "Our People and Their Cities" Conference materials (2 sets in presentation boxes), 1966; 2014:FA407:062 (Box 211, Item 2014:FA407:062)
          Two sets of material in presentation boxes labeled for Stephen R. Currier and for Jane Lee Eddy.
      - Papers and Drafts, 1966 (Box 153, Folder 1518)
        File contains copies of various papers, presentations, and notes. Material had been loosely inserted in a copy of the Background Booklet.
    - Corporate Documents, 1962-1967 (Box 153, Folder 1519)
      File includes Urban America Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws, 1965 and 1967; plus tax filings and audited financial statements for ACTION and American Planning and Civic Association.
    - Currier Memorial Committee, 1967 (Box 153, Folder 1520)
    - Currier Memorial Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 153, Folder 1521)
    - Dawson, David A., 1966-1969 (Box 153, Folder 1522)
      Dawson was Director of Administrative Services and later Assistant Treasurer of Urban America.
    - European Tour
      - 1968 (Box 153, Folder 1523)
      - (Literature), 1968 (Box 154, Folder 1524)
        Publications and brochures.
        The paperback book, German Reality: Documentation on the Division of Germany and the Relations between the Two German States, edited by Rudolf Graf, Hans Gerhard Mueller, and Siegfried Stuebner (Dresden: Verlag Zeit im Bild, [1968]), was discarded in processing.
        - Kokoschka malt Berlin (Kokoschka Painted Berlin) (pamphlet), circa 1966; 2014:FA407:022 (Box 210, Item 2014:FA407:022)
      - (Literature), 1968 (Box 154, Folder 1525)
      - (Literature), 1968 (Box 154, Folder 1526)
        Information packet on Cumbernauld New Town, Scotland, and Bison wall frame system.
      - (Literature), 1968 (Box 154, Folder 1527)
        Tapiola, Helsinki.
    - European Tour
      - 1970 (Box 154, Folder 1528)
      - (Literature), 1970 (Box 154, Folder 1529)
        Publications, maps, and brochures.
      - (Literature), 1970 (Box 154, Folder 1530)
    - Executive Committee Meetings
      - 1965 (Box 154, Folder 1531)
      - 1966 January-July (Box 155, Folder 1532)
      - 1966 August-December (Box 155, Folder 1533)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 155, Folder 1534)
        Materials for 1968 consist only of a budget letter.
    - Local Development Services Division, 1965-1966 (Box 155, Folder 1535)
    - Local Development Services Division, 1965-1966 (Box 155, Folder 1536)
    - Muller, John H., 1966 (Box 155, Folder 1537)
      Equitable Life Assurance Society's membership contribution to Urban America.
    - National Policy for Urban America (City College Conference), 1976 (Box 155, Folder 1538)
      File consists of Jane Lee Eddy's conference folder. Material was originally filed in the Rosters file.
    - New York City Renewal Program, 1967-1968 (Box 155, Folder 1539)
    - Projects (Corpus Christi, Texas), 1966-1968 (Box 155, Folder 1540)
    - Projects (Syracuse University), 1966 (Box 155, Folder 1541)
    - Projects (Tulane University), 1965 (Box 155, Folder 1542)
    - Projects (United States Department of Housing and Urban Development), 1965-1966, 1968 (Box 155, Folder 1543)
    - Projects (United States Department of Transportation), 1968-1969 (Box 156, Folder 1544)
      Includes Urban Design Center proposal "A Process for the Improvement of the Urban Transportation Information System."
    - Projects (University of California, Los Angeles), 1966-1967, 1969 (Box 156, Folder 1545)
    - Projects (University of Chicago), 1965 (Box 156, Folder 1546)
    - Projects (University of Wisconsin)
      Urban America commissioned research project to produce an updated compendium of urban design tools and standards and to update Harry Fagin's "Planning and Community Appearance." File includes memos by C. McKim Norton, 1962, and Fagin, 1964, on creating a more attractive urban environment and visual America, as well as a 1964 report by Fagin, "Concerning a Ten-Year Program for the American Planning and Civic Association"; proposals concerning the education of children in environmental aesthetics, and project reports.
      - 1962-1964 (Box 156, Folder 1547)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 156, Folder 1548)
      - (Report), 1965 November (1 of 2) (Box 156, Folder 1549)
        Urban America Project Report Number One, "Compendium of Community Appearance Measures," first draft, November 1965, pp. 1-175.
      - (Report), 1965 November (2 of 2) (Box 156, Folder 1550)
        Urban America Project Report Number One, "Compendium of Community Appearance Measures," first draft, November 1965, pp. 176-306, and appended sections.
      - (Report), 1966 (Box 156, Folder 1551)
        File contains draft of "The Professional View of Urban Design: A Decade of Thinking as Reflected in Symposia 1956-1966," by Carol H. Tarr.
    - Publications and Reports: General
      Files include general reports, plus: "City," volumes 1-2, 1967-1968; John G. Heimann, "The Necessary Revolution in Housing Finance," 1967; "Crisis: The Condition of the American City," 1968; "The Ill-Housed: A Compendium of Recent Writings and Reports on National Housing Policy," 1969; "The New City," edited by Donald Canty, 1969; and "One Year Later: An Assessment of the Nation's Response to the Crisis Described by the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders," prepared by Urban America and the Urban Coalition, 1969.
      - 1966-1968 (Box 156, Folder 1552)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 156, Folder 1553)
        - City, volumes 1-2, 1967 April - 1968; 2014:FA407:063; 2 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:063)
          Volume 1, numbers 1-4 (1967); volume 2, numbers 1-6 (1968). Spines embossed "Jane Lee Eddy." Volumes may have been enclosed in Donald Canty to John Simon and Jane Lee Eddy, 1969 August 8; see file for Donald Canty, box 15, folder 151.
      - 1968 (Box 156, Folder 1554)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 157, Folder 1555)
      - 1969 (Box 157, Folder 1556)
        - The New City. National Committee on Urban Growth Policy, 1969; 2014:FA407:064; 1 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:064)
    - Publications and Reports: ACTION Council for Better Cities
      ACTION stands for American Council to Improve Our Neighborhoods.
      File includes proposals prepared for ACTION's Local Development Services Division concerning the Hartford Development Fund, the Cambridge Corporation, and Patterson, NJ, housing and urban renewal; as well as materials from the ACTION symposium on "The Troubled Environment: Business Examines Social and Economic Barriers to Improving Our Cities," Washington, DC, December 8-10, 1965.
      - 1964-1965 (Box 157, Folder 1557)
      - 1965 December 8-10 (Box 157, Folder 1558)
      - 1965 December 8-10 (Box 157, Folder 1559)
        - The Troubled Environment: Business Examines Social and Economic Barriers to Improving Our Cities. The record of a national symposium conducted December 8, 9, and 10, 1965, 1966; 2014:FA407:065; 1 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:065)
    - Publications and Reports: ACTION - Housing, 1964-1966 (Box 157, Folder 1560)
      Reports by the Allegheny Council to Improve Our Neighborhoods.
    - Publications and Reports: Local Development Services Division, 1966 (Box 157, Folder 1561)
      Proposal to the Ford Foundation for a second grant to continue the Local Development Services Program, August 10, 1966.
    - Publications and Reports: Local Development Services Division, 1966 (Box 157, Folder 1562)
      Nonprofit Housing under Section 221(d)(3) of the National Housing Act: Illustrative Case Processing an FHA Multifamily Housing Project under the Section 221(d)(3) Below Market Interest Rate Program for Low and Moderate Income Families (New Construction). Urban America, 1966.
    - Publications and Reports: Nonprofit Housing Center
      - 1967 (Box 158, Folder 1563)
        Program reports January-May 1967.
      - 1967 (Box 158, Folder 1564)
        Annual report.
      - circa 1967 (Box 158, Folder 1565)
        "A Proposal to Create the Newark Community Development Corporation." Interim report submitted to the Housing Committee, Greater Newark Council of Churches.
      - 1967-1968 (Box 158, Folder 1566)
        "Housing Revolving Fund: A Proposal for the Washington Metropolitan Area"; "Prospectus for the Urban America Revolving Loan Fund," July 1968; "Nonprofit Housing Rent Supplement Program under Section 221(d)(3)...," 1968.
        - Nonprofit Housing Rent Supplement Program under Section 221(d)(3), 1968; 2014:FA407:066; 1 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:066)
          An illustrative case, showing step by step the processing of an FHA multifamily housing project under the rent supplement program of Section 221(d)(3). By John R. Gallagher III and John J. O'Donnell Jr.
      - 1968 (Box 158, Folder 1567)
        Program report January-March 1968.
      - 1968-1969 (Box 158, Folder 1568)
        Annual report; seminars brochure for 1969.
    - Publications and Reports: States Urban Action Center, 1968-1969 (Box 158, Folder 1569)
      As volumes have been separated, file contains separation sheet only.
      - Action for Our Cities: A Preliminary Report. Part 1: Control of Crime and Civil Disorder. Part 2: Housing. Part 3: Employment and Economic Development., 1968-1969; 2014:FA407:067; 3 Bound Volumes (Item 2014:FA407:067)
    - Publications and Reports: Urban Design Center, 1966-1967 (Box 158, Folder 1570)
      Herb Rosenthal, A Regional Urban Design Center for the West Coast, July 1966; Henry C. K. Liu, "Mid-Career Education for Urban Designers," January 1967; George A. Dudley, "A National Urban Design Center," March 1967; "Urban Design Center Program Proposal," June 1967.
    - Publications and Reports: Urban Design Center, 1969 (Box 158, Folder 1571)
      Proposal entitled "Aggregated Breakthrough Markets," submitted in response to the U. S. Department of Housing and Urban Development's Operation Breakthrough.
    - Rosters
      - 1966-1967 (Box 158, Folder 1572)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 159, Folder 1573)
    - Roundtable on Housing (Dallas), 1966 April 3-4 (Box 159, Folder 1574)
    - Roundtable on Transportation (Pittsburgh), 1966 May 23-24 (Box 159, Folder 1575)
    - Roundtable on the Workplace (Chicago), 1966 June 5-6 (Box 159, Folder 1576)
    - Roundtable on the City as a Whole (New York), 1966 June 12-13 (Box 159, Folder 1577)
    - Sanford, Terry, 1968 (Box 159, Folder 1578)
      Sanford was on the Board of Urban America.
    - Slayton, William L.: Speeches and Papers
      - 1965, 1967 (Box 159, Folder 1579)
      - 1968 (Box 159, Folder 1580)
      - 1969 (Box 159, Folder 1581)
    - White House Conference on Natural Beauty, 1965 (Box 159, Folder 1582)
    - White House Conference on Natural Beauty (Rosters), 1965 (Box 159, Folder 1583)
  - Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB)
    - Grant Awards
      - 1996-1999 (Box 160, Folder 1584)
      - 2000-2007 (Box 160, Folder 1585)
    - Reports and Literature
      - 1988, 1998 (Box 160, Folder 1586)
      - 2000 (Box 160, Folder 1587)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 160, Folder 1588)
      - 2003 (Box 160, Folder 1589)
      - 2004-2006 (Box 160, Folder 1590)
  - Urban Justice Center, 2007 (Box 160, Folder 1591)
  - Urban Land Institute, 1966, 1972-1976 (Box 160, Folder 1592)
  - Urban Pioneering Program, 1993 (Box 160, Folder 1593)
  - Urban Renewal, 1965 (Box 160, Folder 1594)
    Correspondence, conference programs, and clippings on urban design and renewal. Includes paper entitled "A History of Urban Renewal in New Haven."
  - Uris Brothers Foundation, Inc., 1995 (Box 160, Folder 1595)
  - Vanderbilt University, 1966-1969, 1972 (Box 161, Folder 1596)
    Divinity School proposals; Law School and publication of the Race Relations Law Reporter.
  - Vermont in Mississippi, Inc., 1967 (Box 161, Folder 1598)
  - Vermont Law School, 1995 (Box 161, Folder 1599)
    File consists of one letter, referencing the Smokey House Project and land reserve proposal.
  - Verman, Marvin, 1969-1971 (Box 161, Folder 1597)
    Verman, an architect, proposed the use of prefabricated multi-family housing units as a way of addressing housing problems in New York City.
  - Victor-Bostrom Fund Committee, 1967-1969, 1971-1972 (Box 161, Folder 1600)
    The committee was a fund-raising arm of Planned Parenthood.
  - Virginia Council on Human Relations, 1963 (Box 161, Folder 1601)
    Support for study of the Prince Edward County school closing.
  - Virginia Students' Civil Rights Committee, 1965-1968 (Box 161, Folder 1602)
  - Vocational Advisory Service, 1960-1966 (Box 161, Folder 1603)
  - Voluntary Defenders Committee, Inc., 1976-1977 (Box 161, Folder 1604)
    The Voluntary Defenders Committee, Inc. operated under the name Massachusetts Law Reform Institute.
    Support for research and analysis by AmyTotenberg in the area of housing and community development.
  - Volunteer Opportunities, Inc., 1966, 1968-1969 (Box 161, Folder 1605)
  - Volunteer Opportunities, Inc., 1970, 1973 (Box 161, Folder 1606)